so let's look at one example of why we
may need synchronization so let's say we
have two threads and what they're doing
is counting occurrences of different
letters in a letter the first thread
let's call it thread a is counting in
the first half of the document so it's
going to count occurrences of each
letter in the first half of the document
and the second thread let's call that
thread B is counting in the second half
of the document and then they will put
these counts together somehow so the
code might look like this a thread will
load a letter load from memory the count
for that letter add one to that count
and then store the new count back into
memory while thread a is doing this
thread B might be doing this it loads a
letter from its own part of the array
note that R1 and R2 are different in
these threads this is kind of the
pointer to where I got in this part of
the array this is the pointer where this
thread got in its part of the array So
This Thread is doing exactly the same
work as this one and as long as the
letters they're processing are different
this is going to work this thread is
incrementing one part of the count array
this one is incrementing something else
in the count array but what if this
thread sees letter a and this thread at
the same time sees another letter A in
its own part of the array then what
happens is they both try to load the
same element from the count aray let's
say the count was 15 so this one will
load 15 and this one will load 15 now we
add one and we get 16 and we do the same
here finally we store 16 to memory and
here we also store 16 to memory so now
there were two occurrences of letter A
but the value in the array ends up being
16 which is only one more than the
original 15 so after both of these
threads are done updating the counter
the counter should have been 17 so
clearly this is incorrect Behavior what
we need is really that this happens and
then this happens or the other way
around but these should not be happening
simultaneously because then we can get
the incorrect result if for example this
happens first we load we get 15
increment store 16 now when we load this
here cache coherence ensures that we
load 16 and we end up with 17 here which
is a correct result similarly if we did
this first it would produce 16 in memory
then we would load that in increment to
17 so no matter which one of these
happens first we should get the correct
result but we don't get the correct
result if they happen in an interleaved
fashion they should happen one at a time
either this and this or all of this and
then all of this so these things that
have to execute kind of one at a time
are called Atomic or critical sections
so we have one critical section here and
another one here they can actually be
the same code it's just that both
threads are currently in the same piece
of code but as you can see if we have a
section that should behave as a critical
section meaning we do this without
interference from any other thread if we
just let it happen it's not going to be
done correctly so what we need is
synchronization we need additional code
that ensures that only one thread gets
to do this at any given time